I want to talk about 15 years.
I think that you spend on call.
That's a lot of 3:00.
Do you feel like agents will very much be able to take that role from us?
The basic investigations of on call the
the log scraping, the diving into metrics and so on.
You know, if you look at something like AWS DevOps agent, it's great at doing
that kind of automation of, let's say, the more day to day aspects of on call.
And then what's left is the really interesting reasoning about
why is the system behaving this way.
You know, what are we seeing in terms of large scale failures?
What are we seeing in terms of improving performance at big scale and so on.
And, you know, automation is going to help us there a whole lot,
but it doesn't have answers to those questions today.
The AI Native Dev is a podcast for
developers and engineering leads at the cutting edge
of AI and agentic coding. Join your hosts,
Guy Podjarny and me, Simon Maple, every week
as we chat with the most exciting voices
in AI and tackle the biggest questions facing
developers today. This is the AI Native Dev.
Yesterday you were writing code. Today you're prompting agents.
Tomorrow you'll be running a software factory. Agentic
coding is moving fast enough to give anyone whiplash.
This June, AI DevCon London sold out. Hundreds of
developers, engineering leads and VP's packed in to hear
speakers from Anthropic, OpenAI, Netlify, and GitHub, cut
through the hype and get to what actually works.
This November, we're bringing it back to New York.
Bigger, bolder, and full of people actually building
the agentic future. Three days of real talks, real
tools, real answers. Whether you're directing the agents, building
the loops themselves, leading the teams, or setting the
strategy. Our early bird pricing ends on September
30th, so make sure you lock in your place
before prices increase. As a podcast listener, you can
get 15% off your ticket using promo code POD15.
We have so much planned and we can't
wait to have you join us in New York.
Hello
and welcome to another episode of the AI Native Dev.
And joining me today is Marc Brooker.
And Marc is a VP and Distinguished Engineer at Amazon Web Services.
Marc, welcome to the podcast.
How are you? Well thank you Simon I'm great.
It's a pleasure. It's a pleasure to chat.
And you're of course, you're on the West Coast, right? You're in San Francisco.
I'm in Seattle. In Seattle.
A little bit further. Yeah. And.
And so it must be raining.
I assume it's raining there, just like it is in the UK right now.
It is threatening to rain.
It is threatening. Is he the reigning or threatening to it?
As they say, are two weeks of glorious summer and we're back to Seattle.
Weather. Amazing. Amazing.
I was I was on a call with someone from Kenya
today, and weirdly, it was warmer in London today
than it was in Kenya, which was, I doubt there are too many days
where you could probably say that, but it's nice to boast every once in a while.
So, Marc, you've had an illustrious career so far.
Tell us a little bit about,
you know, what you've been up to and some of the work that you do at AWS.
Yeah.
So I've been at W.S.
for a long time, for 18 years now.
Worked on a whole bunch of things.
But the last few years has been really focused on agentic
AI and agentic development tools and, and the infrastructure for, for agentic AI.
And so,
was was deeply
involved in the development of, of AWS AgentCore,
this kind of suite of tools for building agents in the cloud.
But most recently,
I've been focused on building a,
a team, really looking at
some of the future of agent building
agentic development. And,
so we own Strands,
which is AWS agent framework, open source agent framework.
We've got some really cool technology coming in the strand space,
and then we're building some new development tools, thinking a lot
about the future of development, and doing everything ranging from fairly
basic research to a lot of a lot of code building a lot of product building.
So it's a really fun time to really kind of be focusing
on pushing the,
pushing the frontier of, of what it means to, to build software.
Amazing.
And actually, we haven't really talked about Strands too much on the podcast.
Tell us a little bit about, you know, what Strands is and who should be interested.
Yeah.
So Strands is a open source SDK for building agents.
Works with any,
any model, any cloud provider, local agents, etc.
and the goal of Strands is to make it as easy as possible
to build great production ready agents.
And so the kind of minimal Strands agent is just a handful of lines of code,
but you can build out from there with,
tool integrations, you know, or built in MCP
clients, built in open API clients,
context management are
all of the things that go into,
you know, into building a, a great agent.
And the Strands team is really trying to make that as easy as possible.
By being, let's say, very opinionated about good agent patterns.
And, and so you can extend Strands, you can use it any way you want,
but there's a really nice kind of paved path through Strands
that has these opinions of, of what we think right now.
It means to build a great agent built right in.
It's funny because I always think,
you know, developers who have never built an agent before
probably think there's actually so much complexity behind the scenes.
Yeah, but they can actually be very thin veneers around the and
I think
it's, you know, very much encourage people and listeners to actually build that.
And it sounds like, it sounds like this could be a,
you know, a very helpful way of actually doing that from, from, from scratch.
Yeah. For sure.
And, you know,
I really just would encourage people to build build your own development agent.
I mean, it's not going to be as good as, as.
As one of the, you know, major commercial offerings.
But very quickly, even in a couple of hours,
you'll get this much better intuition for what's
going on under the covers of those agents, how they work.
And I think they're kind of experience.
And we will touch on this a lot more
as we talk about how software development is changing.
But that experience of knowing on what's about, what's going on under the covers,
I think just makes people better users of of even the
these great commercial products.
Yeah, yeah. Amazing.
Marc, I want to talk.
I want to go to a little bit of depth now, and I want to talk about something
that was very interesting.
I think you mentioned in a book as well, and it goes back
to the time, 15 years, I think, that you spent on call.
That's a lot of 3 a.m., first of all right.
That's a that's a lot to put anyone through.
That must have been painful.
You enjoy on call.
You enjoyed the those kind of roles. I do.
And I just find them an incredible opportunity for
learning how the real world works, like learning how our systems
actually run, you know, learning what our customers deeply care about.
And, you know, this is one of the challenges.
You come out of university and, you know, I came out of grad school with a ton of
of what I thought was practical knowledge, but a lot of it was quite theoretical.
And then on call was really this huge catalyst over my career
for more deeply understanding how systems
actually work, how systems actually fail, how we can stop them from failing.
You know,
how those things affect our customers and how we can help our customers out.
It's funny, Marc, because I always think a lot of people think they become
a senior developer when they've done five or more years in development.
Whereas actually, I think it's more these types of roles
where you get that real exposure into what it takes to build
a real app that's, you know, reliable and etc., etc..
Is this still, you know, talking about the future
of development with AI, do you feel like this is,
going to continue this, this type of on call is going to continue?
Or do you feel like agents will very much be able to take that role from us?
You know, I think, you know, this is going to be a
this is just a major theme
of, of software, as we're going to see a huge amount of automation,
of increasing automation of the the rote things.
Right.
Oh, you know, there's been, you know,
this kind of failure and that's not new right.
Like if you look at the whole history of cloud
and and computing, this has been a theme, right.
Like we used to get paid for single host failures.
But now,
you know, AWS autoscaling 15 years ago has just started dealing
with those things for us.
And and load balancer Health Check started dealing with those things.
And so we automated those away.
And we're seeing exactly the same thing with, with AI, with the basic,
the basic investigations of on call, the,
the log scraping, the diving into metrics and so on.
You know, if you look at something like AWS DevOps agent,
it's great at doing that kind of automation of,
let's say the more day to day aspects of on call.
And then what's left is the really interesting reasoning about
why is the system behaving this way?
You know, what are we seeing in terms of,
large scale failures?
What are we seeing in terms of improving performance at at big scale and so on?
And, you know, automation is going to help us there a whole lot, but
it doesn't have answers to those questions today.
Yeah.
And I'd like to think that when I do wake up at 3 a.m.
and other early morning times are available, but let's stick with 3 a.m.
that an agent has already been through the logs
and been through all the information, you know, the grueling part of the,
the debugging of or not the debugging per se,
but trying to identify what a root cause could be.
And it's already provided that as part of, you know, the on call where I am woken
up and presented with all the information that I need to make a decision,
I'd love to know
as part of the as part of the, you know, your writing in the past, you've
said, around that you've done around 3000 or you're read
3000 to 4000 postmortems.
I guess what did that teach you?
That you wouldn't have really been able to learn without being on call.
So as a typical developer trying to build,
what did the postmortems really open up for you?
Well, one of them is a deep sense of humility.
You know, as, as we we tend to be optimistic, which is great.
You know, we tend to think, hey, we can build this,
we can solve this problem, which is fantastic.
And then, you know, you see how things fail.
And you see when things don't work and you get a, a dose of humility
from that and a dose of,
sort of closing that loop of, okay, well, I'm going to be optimistic.
I'm still going to believe I can do this,
but I'm going to do it in a better, smarter way this time.
Yeah.
One very concrete thing, for example, is,
you know, over the last ten years
or so, there's been this increasing,
familiarity with a concept
that is now called metastable failures.
These are failures that large systems have where something will happen,
whether it's an overload or a component failure, the system will go down,
the immediate cause will be repaired in the system, won't recover
because it gets stuck in this sort of stable down state.
And, you know, deeply understanding that has been super important
to understanding how to avoid whole classes of long and painful outages.
And I think a lot of our understanding of that, and certainly personally,
a lot of my understanding of that has been come
from looking at real world incidents, looking at when that happens,
and then analyzing the dynamics of the system during those times.
And, you know, we
could have approached that entirely analytically.
We could have approached that from the outside.
But I think we've learned a huge amount more by looking at how real systems fail
both our own and and systems across the industry, and really trying to
extract, like, what was it that kicked the system into the state?
What was it that kept it down?
What was it that led to recovery?
How can we make systems more resilient against those things?
How can we make that recovery faster?
And to your earlier question, how can we build automation that can make
that recovery automatic when it's when we're in one of those states?
Yeah, yeah. Super interesting.
And I think that learning and feedback is super key.
And I think for us as humans, you know, pre AI being mainstream, it's
what we would have learned
and what really would have leveled us up to that senior developer.
And and I think your point on humility is so valuable.
I think,
you go in with a different mindset
when you build code and you think, right, I know this is going to break.
I just don't know how or when.
And you look at it quite differently.
So I love that answer. I think that's brilliant.
I'd love to understand.
We as humans can learn from from not just our mistakes,
but our experiences, our view of other postmortems and things.
How about agents?
When we think about
loop engineering, for example, and we think about how we can take these loops
that will automatically, understand
how agent agents could have done better,
potentially updating context updating skills so that when we write
and build applications that are similar, we can potentially circumvent,
you know, work around certain problems or at least guard against them.
Is that realistic or is that kind of like a pipe dream in terms of the type of bugs
that would be raised to a to a, a postmortem?
Oh, that's very realistic and very much that is, you know what what is happening
today at the at the frontier of these agents with a of techniques.
And so, you know, one of the techniques that you have is to say,
hey, I've got all of these postmortems.
I'm going to put them in the training set of the model.
And so you can improve the model in other ways.
Say, I've got all of these postmortems, and I'm going to give my agent a tool
to search over those postmortems semantically and say,
show me incidents like this one.
And then I can understand how I recovered from that.
And then at that point, that agent can write its own memories and say, I tried
X — it didn't work. I tried Y and it worked.
And so next time it will retrieve from those postmortems,
it'll retrieve from its memories and jump ahead in that in that phase.
Increasingly, agents are also seeing,
hey, I did this step in this step in this step, I could encode all of those
into a piece of code and build myself a tool and put that tool
in my memory, this kind of procedural memory.
And and remember that and just pull that off the shelf when I need it.
And so there is building those libraries of context for agents.
There is building great allowing agents to build and and manage their own memories.
There's model customization and then there's both manual
and automatic tool building for agents and a whole variety of other techniques.
And each of these things can help us make agents,
learn from experience and get better and better at solving certain
types of problems, both more reliably, but also more quickly and more cheaply.
And do you think that loop of learning and understanding,
particularly around, you know, incidents that occur, do you think
that's most valuable during an incident where it can actually learn and understand
where possible root causes are or,
you know, it's likely that it's going to be something like this
because it's the last four was similar or I saw a similar footprint before.
Or do you think that learning can be taken down into the architecture
decisions and the development decisions for future building?
Yeah, well, you know I hope so.
And that's, that's,
that's a bit that we're making I think we haven't seen as much of that yet.
Yeah.
And maybe, you know, to take that back to the human level,
one of the things that we've always done at Amazon is our,
our product teams, the same people who are building our products or on call
for those products.
And we do that primarily because it drives exactly that learning loop, right?
You you get that production experience, you get those customer anecdotes
and you bring them right back into development, whereas separating
those things out into separate teams, although it does have its advantages,
makes that learning loop much harder to drive and much more abstract.
Yeah.
And so when we get into the agent world, what we want is that our coding agents
out of agents are software building agents are learning from production experience
in exactly the same way that operations automation agents are.
And there's a
path to that with with memory, with sharing context,
with sharing those memories, sharing tools, etc.
even using that development agent as a kind of expert
consultant for reviewing a software design.
But I would say as an industry, we are earlier on that journey
than we are on the optimizing the individual pieces.
Nice.
I remember when prompt engineering was a thing
where you used to be able to write something to say like, oh, by the way,
another agent is going to review this, so make sure you do it well.
And I love the idea of just thinking, oh, by the way, you're going to be on call
for the code you write, and you might be woken up at 3 a.m.
Claude or Gemini or whoever. So.
So that that could be that could be kind of fun.
I'd love to know.
In your experience, what can an agent not what's it
not possible for from for an agent to learn from a postmortem.
And I guess this kind of like leans more into where we as humans
need to be very understanding of where we play a role.
So from the postmortem, what's what do you expect an agent just to breeze over?
Well, I think the things that agents can solve are the ones that are,
have clear, definitive outcomes.
Right.
I have a graph of
orders on Amazon.com, or
I have a graph of EC2 instance launches, and it should look like this.
It does look like this.
Figure out why there's that gap and and drive that closed.
Right.
There's a very clear goal.
The ones that are harder to solve
are the ones that are, well,
you know, some I'm hearing on Twitter
that customers are seeing a few more errors than usual or people
are, you know, just seem less happy with the product or,
you know, things feel generally slow when I open it.
And so the more ambiguous things and so, you know, agents can help you
dig into those and can help you find,
find the, the metrics
that might be driving those perceptions from customers or driving those anecdotes,
but generally aren't
as good at really understanding the end to end context of the work.
How are customers using the system?
What does it mean for it to feel fast?
What does it mean for it to feel reliable?
And, you know, as we know, encoding those kinds of things
in metrics is is often very difficult.
Yeah. Very very true.
I'd love to jump across now to
to a move that you made actually after a couple of decades in storage,
compute and database, you moved across to agentic
AI safety and policy, which is actually very topical
given the time which we're which we're recording this episode, of course,
Dario just mentioned about how we how,
you know, anthropic should slow down its its development of models
and is kind of talking about others to do the same.
I know Sam Altman agreed. So did Elon Musk.
First of all, I'd love to hear your opinion on that.
And then secondly, I'd love to understand, you know, why the move?
I'd love to I'd love to go deeper into that.
Into that.
Yeah.
You know, I don't have a opinion to share
on, on on model development and the speed of that,
you know, very, very interesting set of trade offs in that space.
What I will say is a lot of the,
you know, my focus here is on what I'm hearing from, from customers
and what I'm hearing from, from developers. And
one of the
very common themes that I hear from customers is,
hey, we built this awesome agent, we use Strands.
We, we we built this awesome demo.
We put it on AgentCore. It looks great.
The board is super excited about the demo,
but now we're really worried about how we get it into production,
how we make it reliable, how we, you know, make our it's so
our customers can trust that agent to do work on, on their behalf.
And a large part of solving
that problem is this idea of agentic policy, right.
What does it mean for an agent to do the right thing?
How do we very clearly define
what an agent can and can't do?
I you know, what of that belongs to the environment
and the harness and and the containment of the agent versus
what of that belongs in the prompt, what tool, descriptions, etc..
And what our customers are asking for
is ways to think
very clearly, very deterministically, about how to build a box around agents
and say, I'm going to trust this agent to do this thing, this thing
and this thing, but it is not going to have any access to do,
you know, these things.
And a lot of people approached that
as a classic authorization problem as you would with, with humans.
Say, hey, I you know,
this human has this authorization to do to, to to take this step.
But humans have a level of judgment.
They have a level of feedback that agents lack,
and classical authorization languages lack a lot of the power
that customers are looking for, for describing what their agents need.
And so, for example, one of the things we did is
we recently launched dogwood, which is this new policy language.
Happy to to go into depth on that.
But that is is built as a specialized language for describing
with mathematical certainty what an agent is allowed to do,
what order it's allowed to do it in, whether it can do thing
A or after thing B, and so on.
And so it really all comes out from these customer needs.
And the fact that, you know, across the industry, people are saying, hey,
agents are super exciting.
We're really excited about what we can do with agents.
We want to automate more.
We want to serve our customers better.
We want to spend our humans time doing more important tasks.
And a key to doing that is having a great security story and a great policy
story, a great isolation story, a great identity story.
And so we can build agents that we can trust
to run autonomously and do critical things within our companies.
And I was going to mention autonomous, actually, because I think that's the key
in terms of
being able to increase our trust and allow agents to run things more autonomously,
we need them to essentially be able to make more decisions, to run
longer processes, and they need that understanding,
or rather, they need that level of,
those boundaries, those set deterministic boundaries without
having to make their own decisions or do anything in a non-deterministic way.
They need those boundaries whereby they can say, yes,
you can, you have access to this, or you can do this or no, this is, you know,
beyond what we want to provide you with in this container or this space.
I think that's, you know, so important.
And I think the last month or so has actually shown how important that is
in terms of, in terms of that belief and trust.
And as we go forward with autonomy
and into factories and long running processes.
How do you see people
using this kind of a tool to, to, to, to run their containers?
Do you see like configurations
that people will essentially be assigning on various tasks?
How would someone set this up?
Yeah.
Well, one of the things that we know from decades of, of research into,
into psychology and operations and operators is that humans are really bad
supervisors are, you know, just really bad at watching
things go by and pushing the red button when something bad happens.
And, you know, there are multiple dynamics behind that.
You know, one of them is this classic research from the 80s.
This is great paper called The Ironies of Automation about how, you know,
as, as an, you know, a system becomes better and better and better
are the failure modes become weirder and less frequent,
and becomes much harder for the human supervisor to understand
when they happen, recognize them, and react correctly to them.
And so I think the only solution to this is that autonomy.
Right? Pull the human out of the loop.
Make them not watch the loop go round and push the button
when something bad happens.
Certainly not make them say yes, yes, yes, off to every, you know, code
generation task because you know who's going to do that.
But instead pop the human out and say,
let's start by describing what good looks like.
Let's start by describing the set of things
that you would like the system to do.
And then once we have that description, we will apply it to the agent
without requiring a human to go around and do those things.
And so how do you do that.
Well some of that is encoding of it's encoding of common sense.
Right. You know
as you develop a piece of code,
you know, what kinds of interactions it should have with the system.
Right.
It's going to do, you know, get pull and get push,
but only in the, the, the repository it's working in.
Right.
If it goes and tries
to do a git push to a different project, well that's probably bad.
And so we're going to encode that little piece of common sense
into a policy.
And part of that is writing
that kind of library of those, those common sense policies.
Part of that is this process of natural language to policy, where you can say,
you know,
this can read anything on my hard drive except the stuff in my secret documents
folder and have that automatically and reliably turned into a policy.
And then part of that is going out
over a company and discovering all of the policies and practices
and so on, and encoding those existing practices in, in the policy.
And so to answer your direct question,
I think the minority case is people writing policy directly.
I think there are going to be some people writing dogwood or cedar or OPA
or whatever, you know, policy language they're using, but the vast majority
are not going to engage at that level and don't want to, because those languages
are are quite specialized and fairly difficult to learn.
But instead are going to be engaging at that natural language level of saying,
you know, here's what, here's what good looks like.
There could be me
as a developer saying, here's what good looks like for me as a person.
Or it could be, you know, somebody in the CISOs office saying,
you know, here's what good looks like for us as an organization.
Here's our our standard in policy for handling customer content
and our standard and policy for handling our code and then encoding those.
And often all of those things will come together.
And so I'll have some things from my CISOs office.
I'll probably have some things from legal,
I'll have some things from myself as a developer.
And all of those go together and provide the shell around my agent
where we can strongly and deterministically make sure
that the agent is following all of those policies
by using one of these lower level languages. Yeah.
I was going to ask actually whether you see this as something in your experience
that is an organizational level or a department level.
From legal from
security, is it is it majority from those from those teams
down to developers, or is it a is it,
you know, closer to a 5050?
I think it's closer to a 5050, right.
Like there is some things that my security teams deeply care about, right?
The way that customer content
is, is handled and where it is allowed to be in a system, for example.
And I want every developer in the company's
agents to be held to maintaining that standard.
And then there's some things that my security teams don't care about, right.
Like can my development agent delete documents from my documents folder?
Well, my security teams don't really care about that because there's no,
you know, there's no customer impact of that.
There's no organizational impact of that.
But as an end user, I care about that super deeply.
I don't want that stuff deleted.
And so I'm going to it's going to be a mix of these things.
And you know, especially as
we get down to individual developers, we know that across the industry.
And certainly, you know, even within teams
and within organizations, development practices vary.
There's a there's a wide range of of what normal looks like.
There's a wide range of tools that people use.
And so just like most big software
organizations don't try and push down a, you will use exactly
these tools at this time type software engineering practice,
they're not going to succeed at pushing down a complete end to end.
This is, you know, your your agent policy because that needs to be adapted
to the kinds of development you're doing and even day to day.
Right.
Like sometimes I'm writing Rust code and I want to set
a certain kind of standard, and I want to write things like,
hey, you aren't allowed to commit before Clippy is happy with with this code.
And sometimes I'm writing, you know, a quick and dirty
prototype of a, you know, of of of a web demo.
And I don't want to sit any of those standards.
And I'm just like,
okay, we'll just hack this thing together with whatever tools make sense,
because we're going to show it all for 15 minutes and then discard it.
And so I'm going to have different policies.
And so those policies do have to come from
from different places and be dynamic and be contextual.
Hey everyone! Hope you're enjoying the episode so far. Our
team is working really hard behind the scenes to bring
you the best guests, so we can have the most
informative conversations about agentic development, whether that's talking about the latest
tools, the most efficient workflows, or defining best practices. But
for whatever reason, many of you have yet to subscribe
to the channel. If you're enjoying the podcast and want
us to continue to bring you the very best content,
please do us a favor and hit that subscribe button. It
really does make a difference and lets us continue to
improve the quality of our guests and build an even
better product for you. All right, back to the episode.
I want to go to another piece, that you wrote about,
which is the software development hypothesis.
And you also mentioned,
a number of different kind of
like forms of this, which is the weak form, strong form, and strongest form.
I'd love you to walk us through the agentic software development
hypothesis first.
Then we can kind of cover the rest.
Yeah.
I'd have to remind me exactly what I wrote in
in that post.
But it's entirely it comes down to this idea
that the hard part of software building is,
I'm going to say specification building.
And, and what that means is describing what you want,
and describing what you want in
sufficient detail.
That it is
it's a complete description of, of what you want.
Once you have that specification, once you have that what you want written down.
My belief is that we're going to see the building
and maintenance of reliable, efficient implementations
of that software become, over time, entirely automated.
We're going to see that first.
And I think we've already seen that with, let's say, these closed specifications.
Hey, I want something that implements this type of file format.
And it's very well described
and we've already seen that.
And we're going to see that grow to larger and larger systems, systems
with more UI systems with more complex interactions.
But I think over time, all of that
kind of specification down of software
development is going to become automated
and driven by an automation loop.
And, you know,
the kind of stronger claim is that the vast majority of software
can be specified crisply
enough to enable that kind of automation.
Yeah, absolutely.
Now, in that same post, you mentioned that very few tasks
have complete specifications,
and you also talked about oracles that can be deterministic.
And you mentioned oracles aren't deterministic.
So I wonder, are we relocating
the, the, the tough piece of the problem
to be in identifying an oracle that's deterministic or being able
to create that complete specification, is that still more of a human issue?
Yeah, for sure.
I think that is where the you know,
where where a huge amount of the human, the human work comes in
is, is creating those oracles, creating those specifications.
And, you know, in some sense.
Testing
is now the most important part of software development.
And, you know, some people will say that it always has been,
but it's never been the, the shiny object for, for most developers.
But now the thinking about how do I build a test that says, you know,
whether this piece of software is good or not?
Is is just really at the frontier
of, of, of software development.
And some of that is going to be specification.
You know, can I write in a formal enough way
to describe that in a deterministic way?
And again, like if I'm implementing Jesus or something.
Yeah, I can, I can fully specify those.
You know, if I'm implementing a
UI for a customer, maybe I can't.
And so I have to use other forms of, of correctness,
oracles, other forms of evaluation that might be more open
ended, there might be customer in the loop, etc., where, you know, we
we get that feedback and feed it back in.
And you know, this
there if you look at,
you know, the kind of automated reasoning level of specification, there's been
this incredible progress in specifying
software in languages like lean
and a huge growth in just addressing bigger
and bigger chunks of of software with that.
But as we expand those components to entire systems and those systems
have complex interactions and so on, that becomes more difficult.
And so I also want to build,
build these oracles that can look at a system and say, is this working well?
And that might be looking at those production metrics that might be
looking at customer feedback.
It might be,
Comparing it, doing a
a fuzz test between two implementations of a database
engine, for example,
and a wide variety of other techniques.
Yeah.
And it's it's so cool to see.
I remember back in the early days, I think we had some folks from Amazon for
when we talked about Kiro, when that was first launched back in the early days.
And yeah, specs.
Specs are such an important piece.
And I think there,
the, you know,
it's definitely got a place in a development for me
in terms of being able to truly describe a function of feature and app
and be able to have that as the source of truth going forward.
I think.
I think there's a super compelling piece there.
One thing I always kind of struggled with
was delineating almost what is part of the specification
and what is part of the test, because very often you can write
something in a specification that is essentially describing a test.
And, you know, similarly when you when you're talking about a test
writing or describing a test,
you're actually talking about how something should function,
which is kind of part of the specification.
And for me, almost like the the functional specification
as part as well as the, as well as the tests almost merged into one.
And it's like, well, it could be both, it could be the same thing.
But but yeah, super, super interesting to see how that
yeah.
You know, and testing is a, I would say informal specification technique.
And, and you know, always, always has been,
you know, I love the things the team has been doing with,
with, with spec-driven development is been some incredible advancement there.
I think looking back on that,
the thing I feel
a little bit about unfulfilling, about the current,
let's say, current moment in spec-driven development
is there's still quite a lot of conflation between what are those requirements,
those kind of declarative requirements and the more implementation detail stuff.
Right.
Like they still oh, well, you know, I want to build this in this language
or for this kind of UI or
and ultimately,
I don't want to care about those things as, as a system builder,
I want, you know, great decisions to be made,
but great decisions to be made more automatically.
And the specification and the tests and so on should focus on what good
looks like for the output of the software, not for the way that it works inside.
Yeah, no. Super interesting.
I want to now switch.
A little bit to talk about.
I think this is a this is something that you said a while back.
I'd love to know if it's still true
that you won't let AI wrote a word of your blog,
but you're very comfortable with it writing
AI generated code for you.
So first of all, is that is that still the case? Yep.
That's right. It is still the case.
What's the difference between blog content and code?
Yeah, it's a really great question.
And so I think it's it's a difference in intent.
And so I think, you know,
five or so years ago I would have said with a strong conviction
that the purpose of most code is to communicate with humans.
And the execution of
that code is important, but not its primary purpose.
And so I was always, you know, very big on comments, very big on
naming things carefully, very big on writing code in a way that communicates,
especially the intent of, of of the code.
I think that's changed and is very quickly changing
across the industry as,
you know, as humans get out of that code level
into more of that kind of specification level,
as a lot of that coding becomes fully automated,
is code is turning more and more into purely implementation
vehicle rather than a communication vehicle.
My blog, on the other hand.
Right.
I'm saying,
this is for people to read and for people to engage with.
And in my mind, there's a kind of social contract behind that,
where I'm saying
I've spent a bunch of time deeply thinking about these words.
I'm going to share these words with you.
And what I'm hoping you're going to do as a reader is
spend some time deeply trying to understand my words.
Whereas if I get Claude to write a blog post for me in five minutes
and then let's say 10,000 people read it and they each take,
you know, each spend ten minutes reading it, there's this huge asymmetry
between the amount of effort that I'm putting in
and the amount of effort that my readers are putting in.
And I think that is unfair.
And if I take that into into work, like Amazon's very doc driven culture,
I write a lot of documents for work,
about plans, about technology, about the things we're doing.
And again, there is a contract between me and the readers,
and I am expecting them to deeply read and understand and engage with my words.
And they're expecting me to have deeply considered
those words and have full ownership for them.
And, you know,
if they're Claude's words, I haven't done that.
And then the third part of that is,
you know, if you have an idea and want to share it with me
and want to share Claude's thoughts on it with me, actually, I think that's great.
But let's do that.
Let's make that interactive, you know, send me the prompt.
Let's, let's have a have a chat with it.
One of the cool things about these, these, these agents that I can go
around the loop and ask follow up questions and so on.
And so if that is the mode of communication we want to choose,
let's choose that mode of communication.
It's not just land in the one that's in the awkward middle, which is,
you know, all of the human care taken out
without adding in the interactivity and possibility
for follow up questions and so on, with which go into that, that interaction.
Super interesting.
And I think it's yeah, for me, I really I really love the way you say,
you know, you care about the fact that it's people's time
and there's a, there's a obviously one to very many,
you know, people who are going to be reading that
and taking the time to read that versus one person's time to actually write it.
Well, in your words,
kind of something that strikes me here is the
you've obviously got the way you say something and then the,
you know, the core of what you're trying to convey,
are both as important as the other to you there,
or if you could get Claude to be able
to write something in a reasonable way.
But the the, you know, if it could,
if it could really capture the message you're trying to share,
would would that be reasonable?
I guess the thing I'm saying is, what would it take
for you to allow AI to be able to write on your blog?
Yeah.
That's a good question.
And at some level, for my personal blog, it is a philosophical thing where I just,
you know, I want to say, this is my, you know, these are my thoughts
as I wrote them with my mistakes, as I wrote them and so on.
I think for those, you know, kind of work documents, I,
you know, if I could get Claude to write succinctly,
you know, just describe the context, pull in the business context and so on.
For me, I would feel quite,
you know, feel quite comfortable with that.
And so maybe the distinction there is, if you're using Claude as an expander,
right, saying here's a prompt, turn it into a six page document.
I think that's a waste of the reader's time.
However, if you're using Claude as a context provider,
right, like add a paragraph with the business metrics for this week,
I think that's fine because you're you're bringing in
new information from the human, and it is almost exactly the same form.
I would have done that.
I would have done that manually. Yeah.
But I think for my blog, you know, I still
I still think there is a level there
which I want to say, it's a piece of craft.
Yeah. I was that's the word I was going to use actually.
It's about can you scale craft.
And I think sometimes craft is best left as a craft.
And, and that's where people get the joy in both creating it
and also consuming it, knowing it's not just, you know, there's no chance of slop.
It's it's come straight from the straight from the hand.
And I think
in terms of, you know, feedback, I've certainly had a play.
And I think it's very, very hard to be able to capture
that level of feedback that still,
you know, offers a, in a genuine way,
the written word, in the same way that a, an individual would write it.
So I really like that.
While on the topic of feedback, let's, let's jump into the kind of advice
or being, you know, being able to suggest what our listeners can do
in terms of feedback signals, that agents can use.
What's the what's the you know, one of the key most important things
that team can do today to improve the feedback signals.
So to to make sure that agents get the clearest signal
to use to, to improve on future runs.
Yeah.
So I think.
The answer to that varies a lot about sort of where
in the agent,
development maturity hierarchy you are.
And so there are a lot of teams still in our industry or just starting out, right,
who are just getting their, their feet with, with agents.
And there's just a huge amount of, I think the things that a lot of people
would sort of roll their eyes at now that are very effective like that.
Agents file and writing, you know, some directions
for the agents about what good looks like into those things.
You know, definitely not a cutting edge technique,
but something that is proven to be effective.
And I think a lot of teams early on try and jump to the end and say, well,
I'm going to do parametric memory or something when you know, you can't ship
code, and till Clippy is happy with it and it passes all the tests,
is a very effective
thing with very little, you know, very little,
overhead.
Then, you know, as we go up,
those are the, the maturity spectrum.
I think where things get really interesting is
making sure that agents have a way
to remember
team context and remember past conversations.
And part of that is just
agentic memory, the kind of memory that is built into a lot of the agents.
They will remember things across sessions.
And if you say, don't do this again, they'll remember it sometimes too well
and sometimes too much.
And that can be annoying.
But the problem with agentic memory is that it doesn't
spread well across,
across teams or even across people.
And so you need a way to capture those memories and to write those down
in a way that the whole organization or the whole team can use them.
And this is where I'm seeing a lot of people use these agent wiki
type patterns,
which are quite popular right now, where essentially I have my team agents,
maintain a
number of just a small wiki of pages about what what good looks like,
and that is shared between,
between the agents.
And then there are tools like AWS context that allows agents to build
a formal graph of,
of the context in its environment, connect that back to memory,
can connect to documents and do that across
an organization.
And part of
that is that dynamic discovery and learning.
And part of that is pulling in the right information
from my organization, where I already have a whole lot of that written down.
Yeah.
And again, you know, people sort of roll their eyes at rag
and be like, oh, well, that's so 2004 or 2024.
But the bottom line is that giving agents semantic search
over the information in my organization is still a super powerful technique.
And so there's just a lot of that I'm going to plumb that in.
I'm going to give give my agent access to that.
And what we're seeing with the
with the commercial agents, especially if you look at something like Kiro
or you look at something like Q from Amazon,
more and more, they're making it very easy to pull in that organizational context
and put in their team context and share those memories through things
like AWS context to bake in what these good kind of learning
from experience patterns look like across across an organization.
Amazing.
I'd like to wrap now by a question
in around advice, but advice to individuals and vice to,
you know, perhaps juniors.
And let's circle back all the way back to the, to the, to the front of this,
to the top of this podcast episode where we talked
about the 3 to 4000,
postmortems that that you've read in the past
and how that very much helped you and you learned from that feedback.
Your advice to juniors is
own a project, talk to a customer, own a deadline, and going back to the front.
Also essentially learning from those mistakes
that we as teams and individuals have made in the past.
But historically, these are the these are the tasks that senior developers
have historically done and often guarded.
Do you think it's reasonable to expect senior developers to now give these types
of tasks to junior developers, or do you feel like they're going to hang on?
And I guess this is the age old question about how we,
you know, how we bridge that gap between a junior and a senior developer.
Yeah. Well, we have to.
You. Know, I think.
The software industry is going to grow, you know, just a huge
amount in importance and economic impact over the next decade.
And the bottom line is
we're not going to do that growth and we're not going to have that growth if
we pull up the ladder and,
you know, the community of software engineers just gets grayer and grayer.
You know, we're not going to build this, this fantastic
new industry on a,
you know, bunch of folks with with gray flakes in their beards,
and, you know,
experience and seniority and, and,
you know, having having been around still matters a huge amount.
Deep expertise still matters a huge amount.
But we absolutely need to build this industry
on a strong culture of teaching and growing
and bringing new folks in training and learning.
And it's tough to know exactly what that's going to mean
technically, day to day, right? Like what?
What does that look like?
But I have no doubt that that is going to be a critical part
of what what our successes in industry is going to look like
and what the success of individual organizations is going to look like
is figuring out what is that path for, you know, bringing people
in from things like universities who often have, you know, fantastic,
and very
fresh theoretical knowledge and, and ramping up on the,
on, on the practical knowledge on the day to day.
And we've got to figure it out.
It's going to be a big differentiator for organizations going forward.
Their ability to bring in new people and bring in new ideas.
And the benefit of that is, is the folks that I see coming out of college
who spent a ton of time learning with AI, learning with agents,
you know, with, without, you know, some of the preconceived
notions a lot of us come towards them with,
just come in with so many fresh ideas and perspectives and, and that's a fantastic,
you know, addition to an organization or a development team to.
Yeah, I totally agree.
And I think it's it's like you say like almost
like a joint responsibility from the organization
and senior engineers to make sure that, you know, these folks are included.
The juniors are included in a lot of the decision
making and brought up to speed on this.
And I think it's it's a very understated,
understood thing that actually junior engineers,
they are truly AI native like, you know, from our point of view,
we've got years, decades of, of of, you know, development.
And, you know, this old way of tapping a keyboard and code comes out.
We're trying to learn the new AI ways, the, our native ways.
But people who will, you know, come through,
you know,
the newer courses, the newer curriculums, which are truly very AI focused.
This is how they grew up, this is how they learned it.
And I think we can absolutely learn from the from the fresh perspective.
So very much plus one to that.
Marc, this has been this has been a wonderful chat I really enjoyed.
I really enjoyed the, the conversation and in particular.
Some of your insights, particularly, I love the fact that you that you read
for 3 or 4000 or postmortems and things like that.
And, Marc,
you've written a number of pieces, blogs and things like that about all of this.
It's actually been it's you have a very insightful blog with all of this.
So on, where can people go to to read that?
Yeah, you can go to my blog. It's at Brooker.
And I tend to share things
on, on, on LinkedIn and a couple of other, a couple of other social platforms.
But my blog and its RSS feed, very old school is is the primary source.
Amazing.
Marc, thank you so much for your time and sharing all that wisdom with us today.
Well thank you Simon.
It's been super fun talking to you today. Amazing.
And thank you very much for listening.
I hope you enjoyed that and tune in to the. Next. Episode soon.
Bye for now.
The AI Native Dev is brought to you by Tessl,
the package manager for skills and context.
Your hosts are Guy Podjarny and me, Simon Maple.
Our producer is
Tom Dowler. The AI Native Dev is not just
a podcast.
It's a community and we host monthly meetups at the
Tessl offices in central London.
Visit tessl.io/community to learn more and I hope to see you there.